Hello, and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be
practicing stoichiometry together.
And the whole entire idea here is
we're going to be mapping out all of
the different types of stoichiometry
because over the, over the past series of
weeks, I've been posting many different
videos on gas law, stoichiometry
solutions, stoichiometry, Mass to mass
stoichiometry, enthalpy stoichiometry,
there are tons of different versions
of how all this can be converted.
Now when we're kind of mapping it
all out, the big thing is, well,
what do they all have in common?
What links them all together?
And the big thing is what brings
them all together is the mole, right?
The goal in the end is always
the mole, meaning how exactly
do we convert to that point?
Okay.
Right?
Stoichiometry is taking the balanced
chemical equation and essentially using
it to define multiple ratios to be able
to predict how much of a chemical compound
we can make, how much do we need, maybe
how much we can theoretically have.
There are all kinds of important
concepts that link all of these
different factors together.
together.
And that's what we're going to be
doing today is mapping them all out.
Now, one thing is, like I said,
we're going to, this is all coming
down to predicting and balancing.
So it's taking all these skills together.
So this is a little bit
more of an advanced video.
That's something that's
more, are you ready for it?
After going through all these little tips
and tricks after learning about how to
balance and go through chemical reactions.
Now, the types of problems that you're
going to be seeing Or could be, could
very much range depending on, well, what
is it that your problem could be asking?
You have to be able to solve limiting
reactant problems, meaning you're
starting with two different masses and
you want to know what runs out first.
Um, you want to know maybe how much
you will make in a chemical reaction.
So how much product do you have?
How much do you need, which is
how much reactant do you have?
Maybe you need to calculate the mass,
or the volume, or the molarity, or
moles, or energy, or even going back
to particles with Avogadro's number.
There are many different concepts that
you can calculate once you get to moles.
And then finally, maybe you have to do
percent yield to determine how good was
your original number using molar maps.
So let's take a look at it, trying to
put the entire thing together to see what
does a molar map look like and trying
to convert from one thing to another.
It first came to understanding a mole map.
The whole idea is where exactly you were
starting, which was how much, when you
start with grams, You could use molar
mass by looking at your periodic table,
defining the molar mass, and you could
convert that to a number of moles.
Now, from there, you had essentially the
chemical equation that is balanced in
the middle, and you can go from moles
to moles using that chemical equation,
searching this new chemical's molar mass
again, and then convert it to grams.
This is what was learned
back in Chapter 5.
Now, from there, you went even beyond
that and learned even more concepts.
Which all started with actually
just looking at gas laws.
Now when it comes to gas stoichiometry,
the whole idea here is you were using
the ideal gas law to bridge this even
farther, expanding this concept of moles.
Right.
If you were given the gap of the
volume of a gas or its pressure, maybe
it was temperature, you could use
the ideal gas law to get to moles.
You could also use STP as well, using
molar volume to bridge that gap as well.
There were multiple pathways.
So gases got brought into the equation.
Now, was that all there was as well?
Well, we also had solutions to So if
we wanted to complete this picture,
we also had the concept of molarity
using solutions, right, where we
could essentially link together taking
the volume or the concentration of a
solution and convert that to moles.
There were all kinds of different moles
and pathways to get to this middle step.
So use this to really be able to try
to help you map out your guideline,
because remember, even though your goal
is the mole, which is right here in
the middle, you always want to let your
units guide your process to be able
to see how exactly are they canceling.
So that way you can get from one
step to the next when you're going
through all these individual steps.
Let's take a look at some of these
chemical react, some of these different
problems that are going to be.
Bridging between all these
different pathways to be able to
map out, get our final answer.
So we're going to be kind
of crossing borders here and
mixing everything together.
Let's take a look.
An amount of nitrogen gas must be
produced in an instant in airbags.
So the first thing you always
need to do is you need to
balance the chemical equation.
And sometimes you might even
have to predict it depending
on what's given to you.
So this is always if it's needed.
Now if we look at this problem,
we can see sodium nitride breaks
down into sodium and nitrogen gas.
And you can quickly see that it is not
balanced right on the left hand side.
We have three nitrogens on the right,
you have two, so something's wrong.
So with this, one of the ideas,
the quick little pro tips is
let's even the odds, meaning you
have three nitrogens on the left.
So how can you even them out?
Well, let's add a two here to make
a total of six, which is now even.
So being that that is even, what we
will now do is we'll put a three in
front of the nitrogens over here, making
six and six on the left and the right.
Then we will now even out the
nitrogens, making the problem balanced.
So now let's actually get
to the actual problem.
So with this, assume you have 65.
1 liters of nitrogen gas, and this
is needed to inflate an airbag.
How many grams of sodium nitride
is needed at a pressure of 1.
06 bar?
atmospheres and a
temperature of 298 Kelvin.
All right.
Now, the first thing you always need
to do is when you're looking at these
problems is essentially find all the
important pieces of information, right?
We see that there's a
volume here of nitrogen gas.
We see that there's a pressure.
We see that there's a temperature and
there's also an R value listed here.
That's kind of letting you know,
Hey, this is a gas law problem.
If you have pressure, Temperature,
that's a big red flag that should be
going in your head that this is gas law.
Another thing that can pop up is if you
see the letters STP being presented,
that's telling you also a context clue.
Now it's asking you how many
grams there are in sodium nitride.
Well, you can't use the ideal gas
law to get directly the grams, but
you can get two moles of a gas.
And then you can use the chemical
formula to bridge that gap, right?
So going from one step to another.
So what we are going to do is we need
to map out our moles and write down
all the key pieces of information so
that way we can see exactly what it
is that we had in the problem, right?
So we had 65.
1 liters of our gas that
was presented to us.
We have our pressure written down.
Um, so what can we start with?
Well, if we have a volume, what we can
use is the ideal gas law to get two moles.
Now from there, what, being that we
have a balanced chemical equation here
at the bottom, we can use the mole
to mole ratio, being that all this
data here is representative of how
many moles of sodium you have, right?
So that is this purple area here.
And what we are going to do is we're going
to use that to convert to moles of sodium
nitride because it's asking, okay, how
much did you essentially, did you start
with in this problem to solve for that?
So going from purple to red.
Now that's using our chemical equation.
Now we use molar mass to finish the job.
So let's, let's work that out.
Let's do it.
So the first thing we need to
do is we're going to use our
Gas law to solve for moles.
So why don't we do that for ourselves?
So if we are to kind of look at
this, uh, problem up here, so
using our gas laws to kind of solve
this, let's move our r value up.
So the first thing we need to do is
we need to plug everything in and
rearrange r PV is equal to NRT equation.
So.
If we are to do that, we
need to get moles by itself.
So what we will do is we will take
our pv, which is on the left hand
side, and then we'll divide that by
RT and then make that equal to N.
'cause remember, it's
originally PV is equal to N rt.
So we're just moving pieces around.
Now we're going to plug everything in.
So we'll have, uh, 1.
06 times, uh, 65.
1.
So 1.
06 times 65.
1.
Then we're going to divide that by
298 times our R constant, which was 6.
08206 times our temperature,
which is 298 Kelvin.
All right.
Now, I know I didn't write all of
our units in here, but we know in the
end it's going to be making moles.
So when we put this in our
calculator, we'll have 1.
06 times 65.
1.
Okay.
Divided by 0.
0826 times 298.
And you want to probably put
these in parentheses so that
way you solve it correctly.
We'll have 2.
82 moles of N2 as our answer and now what
we are going to do is we want to now look
at our mole map to help guide us, right?
Writing these out can be really
helpful because these problems are
very long and it's easy to kind
of get mixed up along the way.
So our next step was using our mole to
mole ratio using our chemical equation.
So we started with nitrogen gas.
So we have 2.
82 moles of nitrogen.
And we need to go to n na N three.
So we have 2.82 moles of N two, and we're
going to convert that all the way to
moles and then to grams in the very end.
So we have three moles of N two.
There's equivalent to two moles.
Na N three.
And now in order to get this two
mass, we gotta use the molar mass,
the one mole of na n three, and
we'll take sodium, add that to
essentially to um, to three nitrogen.
So by adding those two components
together, so once we do that, we'll
have 65.011 grams of na and three.
And we, what we're going to
do is we're going to take 2.
82 times 2 times 65.
011 and then divide that by 3.
And what we are going to get for our final
answer is approximately 122 grams of NaN3.
This is what is required
to inflate this airbag.
So as you can see, we linked together
gas law stoichiometry with mass
stoichiometry together, right?
It's bringing it all into one.
So when we were kind of going through
these paths, so if we take a look at
our original molar map, we can see
that we started up here where the gases
were given and we essentially went down
using our ideal gas law, two moles.
Went across and then went
all the way straight.
So this is the path that we took to
get to grams desired in this problem.
So notice that we didn't
quite keep going up to gases.
We kind of took, we went straight
rather than making a left hand turn.
Let's take a look at our next problem.
How many milliliters of 0.
280 molar barium nitrate is required
to precipitate as barium sulfate From
the reaction with 25 milliliters of 0.
350 molar aluminum sulfate.
Now, with a lot of these problems,
sometimes you're just given the
names of different reactants and you
have to be able to convert them to
their different chemical equations.
So the first one is barium nitrate, if
you remember barium is a 2 plus charge,
nitrate is NO3 minus, so you gotta
swap drop them and we'll get BANO3 2.
Same thing with aluminum sulfate,
we gotta do the same exact practice.
Thanks.
Now, predicting these, most
solutions, being that we're
dealing with molarity, typically
are double replacement reactions.
So we can see here is
that we have AB plus CD.
So we're going to be doing
inside out, meaning the inside
is going to bond together.
So we'll have aluminum, and we just bring
aluminum ion, so aluminum three plus.
And that's going to be
bonding with NO3 minus.
We're going to trade the
charges, right, swap drop.
So we'll bring the three outside
of nitrate, just like so.
So because we need to balance
those two charges, okay.
So we have ALNO3 minus.
Now the other species that
we'll have is barium sulfate.
So BA is a two plus charge.
Sulfate is a two minus charge.
So they get reduced.
We do not have to swap, drop,
alright, but is this problem done?
And sadly we gotta balance right?
So really the easiest way to do this
is use the polyatomics to balance.
So if, let's say, if I
use the nitrates first.
So if you look at the right hand side of
this problem, we have three nitrates here,
and then we have two nitrates on the left.
Let's even the odds, meaning,
being that we have three on the
right, let's make that even.
So how can we do that?
Let's multiply it by two, making a total
of six nitrates, and then we'll multiply
the left by three, making six nitrates.
So what I'm going to now do is
I'm going to look at aluminum,
so I'm zigzagging to aluminum.
We have two of them.
On the left hand side, you see that
you also have two, so that's good.
Now what about barium?
Well, if I do the same thing with
the nitrogens on the other side, I
see I have three nitrates over here.
So what do I need to do over here on
the right hand side is put three in
front of the bariums on that side.
Now, if you look at the sulfates,
we see that we have three on the
right and also three on the left.
Everything is balanced.
Now what we can do is we can kind of
clean up our work and this will be a
balanced chemical equation, just like so.
All right, so let's, we're going
to use this to be able to do our
different chemical equations.
First thing we need to do
is map out the problem.
So right here I have the balanced chemical
equation that we just put together.
And then I wrote down all the key
parts of information from the formulas
or from the actual word problem.
The most important thing is making sure
you list the values under the chemical
that they're talking about because it
helps keep your brain a little organized.
Now when we're kind of looking at
this, it's always really hard to
figure out where exactly do you start.
Because you have multiple terms that can
theoretically get you to moles, right?
If you remember, molarity or big M is
equal to moles over liters, but the
most important thing in order to get
that to moles is you need to be able
to essentially cancel out the liter
component, meaning you need a volume.
So the only one that does have a volume
and a concentration is aluminum sulfate.
So this is like where the green light
is going to be of where exactly we
can start this problem is that we
can start where aluminum sulfate is.
So what we will first do is we're
going to convert that volume
to moles using the molarity.
And then from there, being
that it's asking us what the
volume is of barium nitrate.
So what is needed to do this problem,
we'll use the mole to mole ratio.
Then essentially, um, times or divide
that by the molarity to get volume.
So let's take a look.
Let's do it.
So the first thing right is
that we were given 25 liters of
our, of our aluminum sulfate.
So we have 25, 25 milliliters
of a L two SO four three, and we
need to convert that to leaders.
Which is always the very first step is
it needs to be in the correct units.
So if we can kind of remember
real quick is that 1000 mLs is
equivalent to 1 liter, right?
And from there we are going to be using
the molarity to convert liters to moles.
Because mole is 0.
350 mole molar molar is equal to 0.
350 moles over one liter, right?
These are equivalent to each other.
And that's one of the hardest
things to kind of remember
is that those are equivalent.
So with that being said.
Is what we are going to do, is we are
going to take that and do 1 liter is 0.
350 moles and that will get us
to moles of aluminum sulfate.
Okay, so Al2SO4.
Now what we're going to now do is
we're going to cancel all of our units.
So we see mLs cancels mLs,
liters cancels liters.
And everything is nice and
cancelled the way it should be.
Now, what is our mole to mole ratio?
Well, this is where we use our chemical
equation to get to barium nitrate.
So, what we can see is here,
is that there's one mole.
of aluminum sulfate, and that's
going to be equivalent to
three moles of barium nitrate.
So it's a one to three ratio.
So let's write that.
So we'll have one on the bottom.
So one mole of aluminum sulfate,
and that's equivalent to
three moles of barium nitrate.
All right.
So that will give us two moles.
Now, what we're going to do for that
last step is, so I'm going to try to make
this a little smaller because I'm kind of
running out of room here, so let's kind of
just shift this over just a hair, and our
last part, what we will do is, in order
to cancel our units, is we are going to
multiply, or divide this by the molarity
of barium nitrate because that was.
Given to us.
So we can see moles, cancels, moles,
and then we will divide that by the
molarity, which if we remember was
0.280, or our molarity from earlier.
Okay, so let's fill that in.
So 0.280 moles is equivalent to one liter.
And then we could see this cancels out.
And then we're left with
volume of barium nitrate.
So what are we going to do here in
terms of the math so we can read this?
So let's kind of clear out some
of the highlighting because it's
kind of taking away the visibility
of all these different components.
So we are going to take 25
milliliters, times that by 0.
350, times by 3, and then divide that by
1000, then hit equals, divide that by 0.
280.
Once that happens, what you should
get as an answer is Um, is about 0.
09375 liters of barium nitrate.
And being that the problem asks for this
to be in milliliters, we'll divide this
number by 1000, or sorry, times this
number by 1000, and we'll get about 93.
75 milliliters as our final answer.
And then being that this problem,
we can try and check for sig figs.
as well.
And I believe so that should
be three sig figs in the end.
So you'd want to round it to 93.
8 as your very, very final
answer, if you were putting this,
um, into the correct sig figs.
So that'd be for three sig figs.
That's how you would solve a
solution stoichiometry problem.
So let's go to the mole map and see
exactly where we, what route we took.
So with this particular problem, we
were doing a solution type of titration
or a neutralization problem where
you're mixing solutions together.
So with this one, where we started
is that we had essentially.
Uh, about how much solution that
we started with in the beginning.
So we were down here where
the solution that was given.
We then went up to moles.
Then we went across and
back down through solutions.
So we, we stuck on the lower side.
This was just using regular
solution stoichiometry, which in
my opinion is still the harder
form of stoichiometry to follow.
So we used molarity as a conversion
factor to get the volume desired.
Let's look at another problem.
60 molar potassium iodide is
combined with 20 milliliters of 0.
530 molar lead 2 nitrate.
How many grams of lead 2 iodide
precipitate So, with this one, we have,
we have a reaction, so I wrote out the
reactants, so potassium iodide and lead
to nitrate are reacting, so once again,
double replacement reaction, so inside
out, so we're going to have the inside
react, so being that it's lead 2, so
it's Pb, and we'll have a little 2 plus.
Now we'll have iodine, which is I minus.
So being that we're going to swap drop
those charges We're going to have I2 and
then PB is going to stay the same with
the same subscript So we'll clean that up.
Now.
We're going to have on the other
side is We're gonna have the outside
react together So we have K which
is a plus charge and the nitrate
which is a negative charge So we
just have K and O3 Is it balanced?
Well, we want to first
look at the polyatomics.
If you look on the left hand
side, you're going to see that
there are two nitrates over here.
And on the right hand side, there's only
one, a single nitrate that is there.
So what are we going to do to fix that?
Well, we will add a coefficient
of two in front of the KNO3.
Now we have two of those.
So we'll zigzag right where we see
that we need to balance out the
nitrates, or sorry, the potassiums.
We have two on the right.
We only have one on the left.
So we'll quickly fix that as well.
And now we have a complete
and balanced problem.
All right, the next thing that we're
going to do is write out all the
piece of information that we have.
We were given our volume, which was 60
milliliters of Ki and a molarity of 0.
322.
Then we have lead nitrate,
which was 20 milliliters with 0.
530 molar.
And we want to know is how many grams
of lead iodide are going to be made.
Now, one thing you might notice is when
it comes to solution stoichiometry,
you need to do both the volume
and the molarity to get the moles.
So where do you start?
And you'll see that you have
all four of those values here.
You have both the volume
and the molarity for both.
So what does that mean?
You have a limiting reagent
problem on your hands.
When you have both volume and molarity.
So we need to solve both of these,
getting to TA or getting to lead iodide.
So let's first do it for
the first one, which is ki.
So we have 60 milliliters of KI
and what we are going to do with
that is we are going to convert
that to, uh, all the way to.
are moles of lead iodide.
So we got to go from milliliters to moles.
So first things first is we need
to get this to liters because we
need to be able to use our Mole our
molarity, which is moles over liters.
So just like we did in the last problem,
milliliters cancels, milliliters.
Now what we are going to have is we
have our molarity, which is one liter
is equivalent to 0.322 moles of ki.
So when we look at this, we can
see, all right, what's canceling
out here, liters of Ki cancels,
and now we have moles of Ki.
Now the next step is going to be
all about trying to make sure that
we get two moles of lead iodide.
So this is where we got to
use our chemical equation.
And we remember that two moles
of Ki, so I'm using teal blue to
match the equation, is equivalent
to only one mole of lead iodide.
These are equivalent to each other.
Now, what that's going to do is when
we solve this, We can see all of our
units cancel out correctly, and this is
going to give us moles of lead iodide.
So when I calculate this,
what we will get is 0.
00966 moles of PbI2.
Now are we done the problem?
Did I solve it and we're done?
The thing is we gotta see, how
much does each reactant make?
Which one runs out first?
So we're going to repeat the same
process, but with lead nitrate this time.
So now we can see that our
milliliters are going to be cancelling
each other out, which is great.
Now we are going to convert
this to liter, to moles using
our molarity for lead nitrate.
So what that is going to be is one liter
of lead nitrate is equivalent to 0.
530 moles.
of PbNO3.
All right, so being that we have that, we
will now use our chemical equation again
to say that, hey, one mole of PbNO32 is
equivalent to one mole of lead iodide.
And when we solve this,
so we'll take 20 times 0.
3, 0.
530, divide that by a
thousand, we will get 0.
0106 Moles of lead iodide.
And now what we're going to be
doing is we're going to compare
essentially the two mole values we got.
So the one that's in green here
versus the one that's in purple and
which one is smaller out of the two.
And you can see at the top one
when Ki was fully used made less.
So this is your limiting reagent.
in this problem.
So we're going to use this to
calculate how much mass we had.
So being that we only made about 0.
0966 moles of lead iodide, the way
that we would convert this is we
would use the molar mass of lead
iodide to do the final conversion.
So, uh, pretty much what we
are going to do here is we
would look up our molar mass.
calculate it, and what we would
have is a pretty big molar
mass for such a tiny molecule.
So lead iodide is equivalent
to about 461 grams of PbI2.
So when we multiply those two
values, you would get about 4.
45 grams.
of PBI2 that is going to be
theoretically created in this problem.
So let's say if we wanted to take
this one more step, which as you
can probably have guessed, being
I said the word theoretical, so
all stoichiometry calculations
are considered to be theoretical.
So if everything goes perfectly.
This is how much you should make.
However, we are flawed, we make
errors in labs, and sometimes
you leave things behind.
So let's say you only
collect 4 grams in lab.
What is your percent yield?
So if we were to do this, you
essentially just gotta take whatever
number you obtain, divide it by
what you theoretically calculate,
so 4 point, or 4 grams divided by 4.
45, times that by 100%, And what we would
have for our theoretical yield is 89.
9 percent as our yield, which
would be a very, very good yield.
That shows that you were very
careful when you were doing your,
doing your, your measurements and
your reaction went to completion.
So let's take a look at our mole
map to see what path we took.
With this particular one, we did have
a, uh, a limiting reagent problem, but
they both started at the same point.
You can have limiting reagents where
you start at two different spots and
you try to get to the same end goal.
You still want to convert to
the moles desired, you would
follow the same process.
So, with this one though, we didn't have
to do that though, which is kind of nice.
We started at the solution level, so we
started down here, and what we did is we
converted to moles desired, we figured out
what was our limiting reagent, right, at
the moles desired, And then once we did
that, we went to the Graham's Desired.
So both of these compounds
kind of went together.
So let's say we had like blue and red
and being that red made a little less,
that one continued to the final step.
It's all about kind of the perspective.
You do them both together and then
you want to see like, okay, which
one goes to the final finish line.
yeah, yeah.
in this example, okay?
So we use the molarity to convert volume,
and then we use the chemical equation
to get to the moles, and then we use
molar mass to get to the final step.
Let's take a look at another example.
Our last example, 0.
625 molar HCl is used in an
attempt to neutralize 27.
2 grams of sodium hydroxide.
What volume is required to do this?
So if we had sodium hydroxide
and it was sitting in a beaker
and we wanted to neutralize it,
well we could add HCl to do that.
It would release a ton of heat
and it would actually be a
very pretty intense reaction.
to do so.
But where exactly do you start?
Well, being that the first thing you
need to do is we got to write out our
chemical equation and then balance it.
So we have HCl, and this is going to
be adding to sodium hydroxide, so NaOH.
So this is a double replacement
reaction, so we're going to be having
the inside bond to the outside.
So sodium and chlorine bond together
to make salt, so Na and Cl, and
then we'll have HOH making water.
Now with this one, it's R, it's balanced
the way it is, which is fantastic.
So what we are going to do is
list out everything we were given.
So we have 0.
625 molar HCl, and we want to know what
is the volume in this case, and then we
were given the mass of sodium hydroxide.
So where can you start?
Well, notice the one thing, so
there's two things to notice.
One is that you are giving a
term that's by itself, and then
one that is a conversion term.
Now, when I say conversion term, remember
that means fraction, so molarity is
moles over liters, so you can flip it.
It's usually never wise to
start with the conversion term
unless it's your only choice.
With the mass, it's by itself,
so you can start there.
Now, the other thing to say is that with
molarity, you need both the volume and
the molarity to start with that value.
We don't have the volume.
You cannot start with that.
So we're going to start with molar mass.
Thanks.
and convert mass to
moles using molar mass.
So we have 27.
2 grams of NaOH.
We are going to divide it by the
molar mass to convert to moles.
So let's do that.
So what, we got to look up what our molar,
our, our molar mass is a sodium hydroxide.
So if you quickly do that, what
you will quickly get is about 39.
997 grams of NaOH.
for every one mole.
So you just take one sodium, add it to
one oxygen, then add it to a hydrogen.
Now we'll cancel our units.
So grams of sodium hydroxide
cancels grams of sodium hydroxide.
Now we'll use our chemical
equation to get two moles of HCl.
So we have one mole of NaOH, It's
equivalent to one mole of HCl, which
is great, but we need to now use the
molarity to convert the last little bit.
So let's kind of make this a
little smaller for ourselves
and we'll extend this out.
So this is where we're going to
use that molarity term, which is 0.
625 moles is equivalent to one liter.
So we want to check that
everything actually cancels.
So moles of NaOH cancels, and then
moles of HCl cancels moles of HCl.
Alright, so this gives us the
volume, which is exactly what we
are looking for in the problem,
right, is, is liters of HCl.
So when we do this math, we'll take 27.
2, divide it by 39.
It equals, then divide that by 0.
625.
And what we are going to
get in the end is about 1.
09 liters of HCl is
required to neutralize this.
That is a lot, that's a lot of
acid to neutralize the space.
So you would have to
measure out over a liter.
Let's do a follow up problem to kind
of show all the different types of
problems you can have, which is if the
delta H of the reaction is negative 55.
8 kilojoules.
how much heat is released.
So you have two options
where to start with here.
You, the goal is when you have delta
H of the reaction, this is equivalent
to the coefficients in the reaction.
So meaning that negative 55.
8 kilojoules is equivalent to one mole
of HCl or one mole of sodium hydroxide.
So should you start with the liters of
HCl or the grams of sodium hydroxide?
I always recommend starting with the
initial information given in the problem
originally, not what you calculated.
Being that most different homework
assignments are auto graded, it's
generally always going off of what is
initially given to you in the problem.
Sometimes you might have to
derive and go further and further
and further in the lab, so then
you could use the leaders here.
But it's usually safer to start
with the number you started with.
So we will start it with 27.
2 grams, and from there you can pretty
much follow almost the exact same steps.
So what we can essentially do is just copy
what we kind of have here on the bottom.
So where we have 27.
2 grams of sodium hydroxide, use that
molar mass, and the only thing that
where it's going to be different is
that one mole of sodium hydroxide.
It's going to be
equivalent to negative 55.
8 kilojoules, and that's for every 1 mole
because of the balanced chemical reaction.
If you had a coefficient of like 2, or
3, or 4, that number would follow suit.
Okay, so, if we were to do
this, you would take 27.
2, times that by negative, uh, 55.
8.
And let me just move this over, because
I'm realizing it's getting cut off.
And you would divide that by 39.
997 and we would get about negative 44.
6 kilojoules of energy is released.
And negative means, what type
of reaction this is, this would
be an exothermic reaction.
So that to let you know.
Alright, so if you had
a label, exo or endo.
Let's go to our molar map
to see where did we go.
So with this particular reaction, we
were given the grams of sodium hydroxide.
Which we then converted to moles
of HCl and from there we went and
used the molarity to get to how much
Solution was desired in this problem.
So it went straight across and then
went down for this particular reaction
So another type of problem and as you
can kind of see that heat is not shown
on this diagram That's because enthalpy
probably is one of the more I would
say not as common type of calculations
that you do Usually you do it a lot in
thermochemistry Um, or so, and typically
after that, you don't see it as much.
That doesn't mean it's less important,
but it's usually values that are given to
you in tables and things like that, and
calculating like bonds formed and broken
if you have to take gen chem one or two.
Uh, so for stoichiometry, usually
we always have to do a lot of
solutions and a lot of masses, which
is a little bit more important.
So this has been the whole idea of trying
to practice these types of reactions.
I hope that this video helped.
It was a little bit of a longer one,
but practice problem videos always are.
If you need help or weren't quite able to
follow, please reach out, let me know, or
hit a comment below and let me know what
you thought, and if you have any types of
questions, I'd be happy to answer them.
Alright, thank you so much for watching,
and thank you for supporting the channel.
Please like and subscribe if you
haven't yet, and I hope to see
you again for a future video.
Alright, I'll see you all later.
Bye now.